Finding Aid for Buckbee Family Papers, 1841-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Buckbee Family Papers 1841-1999 1862-1866, 1898
Buckbee Family
0.7 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
0056 Aa 2 Ac
Civil War and Spanish-American War letters, family photographs, and other materials relating to the Buckbee and Church families from Illinois and Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gift of John W. Buckbee (Donor No. 8946 ) The collection was received in March 2000 and the original letters were added in June of 2004. Additions were received in 2005 and 2006.
The collection is open to research.
Walter Adsit Buckbee and his wife Amanda left Vermont and settled in Ypsilanti, Michigan where they raised four children. Walter later served as a member of the Michigan Legislature beginning in 1838. Their son, Julian Edward (who preferred to be called "Edward J. Buckbee"), served in the Civil War joining the 1st Regiment Michigan Sharp Shooters on January 1, 1863 when he was eighteen years old. He began as First Lieutenant and Adjutant, rose in rank to Major, and later was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel for his actions during the capture of Petersburg, Virginia on April 2, 1865. Before the capture of Petersburg Julian was taken as a prisoner of war and held in captivity from June 1864 until early 1865 when he successfully escaped after several failed attempts.
After the war Julian married Mary Marble "Mollie" Church on November 18, 1868, later settling in Winnetka, Illinois where they opened the Winnetka Inn. Julian also joined the Land Department of the Northwest Railroad in the 1870s. Two of Julian's six children, Julian Edward Jr. and Henry Cheever, joined the military during the Spanish-American War in 1898. Although they both began in Company K of the 1st Illinois Infantry, "Cheever" Buckbee eventually was separated from his brother as he was sent to Cuba and Julian to Puerto Rico. Both of the Buckbee brothers survived the war and were able to come back and begin families of their own, Julian marrying in 1900 and Cheever marrying in 1905. Cheever later became a successful businessman and ran for the Michigan Legislature on the progressive ticket, but ended up losing the race. Later letters in the collection show that Cheever D. Buckbee, son of Henry Cheever, also served in the military in 1942.
The father of Mary Marble Church was William L. Church, who during the Civil War, was appointed by the governor of Illinois to investigate the condition and needs of the men of Illinois regiments. As part of his duties, Church visited and wrote home from such battlefront areas as Vicksburg and Pittsburg Landing. He also wrote letters from Pilot Knob, Missouri and Washington DC. Church was one of two men representing Illinois on the Gettysburg platform during President Lincoln's address
The Buckbee Family Papers includes a variety of material but is most significant for its documentation of the Civil War service of Julian E. Buckbee and for the many letters exchanged with his sons Henry Cheever and Julian Edward, Jr., who served in the military during the Spanish-American War. These later letters provide a unique look into daily life during the war and at home in Illinois at the turn of the century. The letters contain both original and photocopied letters, along with transcriptions, to and from Julian Edward Jr. and Henry Cheever Buckbee during their service from April to September 1898. The photocopies all have matching original letters except for letter dated August 21, 1898, and those that were small notes probably sent with packages.
Other files in the collection include newspaper articles, genealogical information, and other various materials related to the Buckbee family from 1859 to 1999; photographs (duplicates and originals) of family members, scenes from the Spanish-American War, and of the family-owned Winnetka Inn located in Winnetka, Illinois; various letters to and from Julian Edward Buckbee Sr., military documents, and other materials relating to E.J. Buckbee's service in the Civil War; and later family papers which include reminiscences of Julian Buckbee Sr., and letters from Cheever D. Buckbee during his military service in 1942. There are also letters of William L. Church written during the Civil War and relating to his visits to various Illinois regiments. Of special note is a letter he received from Colonel William Gamble describing the operation of Illinois troops at the Battle of Gettysburg.
Subjects:
Bugbee family.; Spanish American War, 1898.; United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 1st (1898). Company K.; United States. Army. Michigan Sharpshooters Regiment, 1st (1863-1865).; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and prisons, Confederate.; Petersburg (Va.)--History--Siege, 1864-1865.; Vicksburg (Miss.)--History--Siege, 1863.; Winnetka (Ill.); Buckbee, Julian Edward.; Buckbee, Henry Cheever.; Church, William L.; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bugbee family.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; United States. Army. Michigan Sharpshooters Regiment, 1st (1863-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Winnetka (Ill.)
Contributors:
Church, William L.; Buckbee, Julian Edward.; Buckbee, Henry Cheever.; Gamble, William.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Buckbee Family papers
  - Letter of Walter A. Buckbee to his daughter at school in Chicago, 1849 (Box 1)
    (original and transcription; also issue of Chicago Daily Tribune, April 23, 1849)
  - Clippings and Family Information, 1859-1999 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and ephemera (Box 1)
  - Civil War Letters and Related Materials (primarily of Julian E. / Edward J. Buckbee), 1862-1926, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Memoirs, "The Story I Tell My Children, being a true story of Capture, Prison Pen, and Escape," ca. 1886 (Box 1)
  - Commission from the State of Michigan giving Edward J. Buckbee the rank of Major in the 1st Regiment Michigan Sharp Shooters, April 11, 1865 (Folder 1)
    (Includes piece of the regimental battle flag and a tintype of E.J.B. shortly after the capture of Petersburg, Virginia)
  - Newspaper, The Union Picket Guard (Paducah, Kentucky), Vol.1, no. 2, September 18, 1861 (Folder 1)
  - Spanish-American War Letters, April-September 1898
    - Originals, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Photocopies and transcriptions, 4 folders (Box 1)
      (The photocopies all have matching original letters except for letter dated August 21, 1898 and those that were small notes probably sent with packages.)
  - Later family letters, etc., 1911-1942 (Box 1)
  - Henry Cheever Buckbee papers (Box 1)
    (include photos from Spanish-American War service)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - The Cuban Campaign of the First Infantry Illinois Volunteers April 25-September 9, 1898 (Box 1)
    (One photograph in the book is of Cheever Buckbee)
- Church family papers
  - Letters of William L. Church to his brother Selden, 1841-1843 (Box 1)
  - Letters to and from William L. Church from the period of his Civil War service
    - Originals, 1862-1864 (Box 1)
      (include letters describing siege of Vicksburg and battle of Gettysburg)
    - Photocopies, 1862-1864 (Box 1)
  - William L. Church miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (include family information, obituary, appointment notices, etc.)